A Finding Aid to the Hugo Gellert Papers, 1916-1986, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Printed Materials, circa 1920-1986; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 3 Linear feet Boxes 4-6, 8, and OV 9
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, and Invitations, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, and Invitations, 1956-1963; 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, and Invitations, circa 1929-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gellert Appearances and Publicity, circa 1930-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gellert Article on Art Young in ALA News, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Gellert Illustrations, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Gellert Illustrations, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
      - Illustrations, circa 1927-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Halftone Printing Block, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Proofs, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Aesop Said So and Comrade Gulliver, circa 1935-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Proofs of illustrations for books by Gellert
    - Elore, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Hungarian-language Newspaper
    - Fasizmus, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Anti-Horthy League Pamphlet
    - The Fraternal Outlook, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
      (magazine cover)
    - Greeting Cards, circa 1937-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Lionel Atwill in The Outsider", circa 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
      (theater handbill)
    - Jefferson School of Social Science Catalogs, 1952-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Magyarok Amerikában, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - May Day Committee, 1951-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Mindentudó Kalendárium, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - New World Review, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - New York World, circa 1926-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Pearson's, 1922-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
      (magazine covers)
    - The President's Speech Illustrated by 19 Artists, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Tavasz a Dunán, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - The Worker, 36 Years, Drawings, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Gellert Periodicals, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - American Dialog, 1964-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - American Dialog, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Art Front, 1934-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Magyar Szó (Hungarian Word), 1953-1959; 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - New Masses, 1926; 1933-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Greeting Card Series, circa 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Hungarian Short Stories, 1953; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - List of Artist Contributors to The Masses, Liberator, or New Masses, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Maps, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Pamphlets, Archival Resource Key; (Covers only scanned) (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets General File, 1935-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Pamphlets General File, 1935-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Pamphlets General File, 1935-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Pamphlets General File, 1935-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, circa 1953-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Artists' Equity Association, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Communist Party, circa 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Foreign Languages Publishing House (Moscow), 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Hungarian Bulletin, 1949-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, circa 1943-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - New Century Publishers, 1945-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - New Century Publishers, 1954-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - United Committee of South Slavic Americans, circa 1943-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Workers' Library Publishers, 1935-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Union-related Pamphlets, 1937-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - United States Government, 1935-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - United States Government, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Periodicals, Archival Resource Key; (Covers only scanned) (Box 5)
    - Periodicals General File, 1918-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Periodicals General File, 1922-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Periodicals General File, 1931-1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Periodicals General File, 1935-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Periodicals General File, 1950-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Periodicals General File, 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Periodicals General File, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - American Contemporary Art, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Amnesty Trumpet, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Bulletin of the World Council of Peace, 1956-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - The Lamp, 1952-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Latin American Facts, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - The Masses, 1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Masses and Mainstream, 1950-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Masses and Mainstream, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Masses and Mainstream, 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Mainstream, 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - New Hungary, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Publicity and Mailings, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 32-36)
  - Publicity and Mailings, 1941-1986; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-26)
  - Song books and Song sheets, circa 1932-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Oversized Printed Materials, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 4, Folders 9, 15-16, and 33-35, and Box 5, Folder 26
  - Oversized Printed Materials, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 9)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 4, Folder 26
- Photographs, circa 1920-1959; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  This series consists of personal photographs, news and publicity photographs, and photographs of works of art. Most of the personal photographs are snapshots, and most are unidentified. There are also two sets of group portraits with Gellert pictured, but other individuals are unidentified.
  The bulk of the photographs are publicity and news photographs, including photos from news agencies and file photos of public figures. Public figures include well-known American communists such as Earl Browder, Tom Mooney, Eugene Debs, Upton Sinclair, and Paul Robeson, as well as famous industrialists and mainstream politicians such as J.P. Morgan, Dwight Eisenhower, Herbert Hoover, and Robert Moses. Some of the photographs appear reproduced in the various publications Gellert helped to produce. Several news photographs are marked "D.W." or "Daily Worker." A few of those pictured were also subjects of Gellert's murals and illustrations. Others remain unidentified. Subjects with multiple photographs are listed in the folder headings, and single instances are filed in miscellaneous files.
  Photographs of works of art include murals by Gellert at Seward Park, a mural by Pablo O'Higgins in Mexico, and Philip Guston's mural for the 1939 World's Fair. Set pieces with illustrations by Gellert are shown during a performance, which may have taken place at the 1945 San Francisco conference of the United Nations.
  - Personal Photographs, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Group Portraits with Gellert Pictured, circa 1930-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Family, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Friends, circa 1930-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 30)
      Included are photographs of Carl Schwartz, Julia Schwartz, Irving Fierson, Nancy Fierson, Dolores Gold, Max Bachner, Jenny Bachner, and other unidentified people
    - Unidentified Buildings, circa 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Publicity and News Photographs, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Earl Browder, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Ben Davis, 1943-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - John Gates, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Tom Mooney, circa 1934-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Paul Robeson, circa 1928-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Upton Sinclair, circa 1930-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Harry Winston, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous Public Figures, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Pictured in box 6, folders 39-41 are Bernhard Stern, Walter Lowenfels, George Morris, Robert Moses, Al Smith, Eugene Debs, Julius Rosenberg, William Z. Foster, Irving Kaufman, Karl Marx, Maxim Gorky, B.W. Atwood, Jan Bratiano, Herbert Hoover, Walter S. Gifford, Eleanor Roosevelt, Edward R. Murrow, Dwight Eisenhower, Fred Seaton, Maud Barger-Wallach, Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, Otto Kahn, J.P. Morgan, Pierre duPont, George Baker, Jr., J.D. Rockefeller, Jr., and Eugene Meyer
    - Miscellaneous Public Figures, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous Public Figures, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous Public Figures, Unidentified, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous Public Figures, Unidentified, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Unidentified People, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Australian Livestock, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Eastern European Culture, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Eastern European Culture, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Eastern European Culture, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Eastern European Culture, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Seward Park Slum Clearance Project, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Theater Production of E. Chodorov's Decision, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Gellert's Seward Park Murals, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Theater Performance with Gellert Set Pieces, circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Works of Art by Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Murals, 1933, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Sculpture and Paintings, circa 1920-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Artwork, 1927-1981; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 7, OV 10
  Artwork includes silkscreen prints, lithographs, woodcuts, sketches, drawings, doodles, designs, sketchbooks, layouts for printed materials, and other print production elements. Artwork is by Hugo Gellert and others, including Philip Reisman, Gyula Derkovits, Anton Refregier.
  Artwork that is part of identifiable, titled projects is filed first, including sketches for Gellert's 1934 book Karl Marx's Capital in Lithographs, and a set of silkscreen prints that he issued as a portfolio entitled Century of the Common Man in 1943. General files for sketches, sketchbooks, layouts, and prints filed after them. Sketches, drawings, and designs include a wide variety of material, from loose sketches and doodles to finished drawings, as well as text design, technical drawings, and floor plans. Notes and writings are common among the sketches and sketchbooks, and the sketchbook dated 1950 also contains a handwritten, autobiographical essay.
  Layouts and prints production elements include sketches, prints, typography, brownprints, photostats, and prints in various states.
  - "American Student Delegation to Russia," Silkscreen Poster, 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Oversized material housed in OV 10
  - Karl Marx's Capital in Lithographs, Sketches, circa 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Karl Marx's Capital in Lithographs, Sketches, circa 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Portrait, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Century of the Common Man, Silkscreen Prints, circa 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Monoprints, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, circa 1939-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, circa 1939-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, circa 1939-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, circa 1939-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbooks, 1950; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Two volumes
  - Sketchbooks, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Layouts and Print Production Elements, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Layouts and Print Production Elements, circa 1953-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Artwork by Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - "Stones" by Philip Reisman, circa 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "1514," Woodcuts by Gyula Derkovits, circa 1928-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - "Sword into Plowshare," Woodcut by Anton Refregier, circa 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Unsigned Prints, 1937, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
      The first print is by Charles White, the last print is by Alexander Stavenitz
  - Oversized Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 10)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 7, Folders 7, 10-11, 16, and 19